Guide to the Margaret Grace Bondfield Papers, 1854-1951 (bulk 1898-1951)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Margaret Grace Bondfield Papers
1854-1951
1898-1951
Bondfield, Margaret, 1873-1953
14 cubic feet (14 boxes, 1 OV folder, and 17 books)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, clippings, speeches, publications, government documents, and other materials concerning Bondfield's work with labor and trade unions, primarily in Great Britain, but also Australia, Canada, the United States and other countries.
Biographical Note
Margaret Bondfield, (1873-1953) trade union leader and first British woman cabinet minister, was born in humble circumstance near Chard, Somerset. "Maggie," as she was known all her life, went to work at age thirteen as a teacher in a state-aided school. Two years later she got work as a shop assistant. Low wages, long hours, and the living-in system sparked her interest in the National Union of Shop Assistants and led to her lifelong involvement with the British labor movement. The organizations with which she was involved included the Trades Union Congress, Women's Trade Union League, National Federation of Women Workers, and the International Labour Organization. On all these fronts she fought for the rights of women workers and for the recognition of women within the movement. As a socialist she opposed the limited bill for female emancipation and stood for adult suffrage.
Early in her career Bondfield joined the Independent Labour Party. In a six-year preliminary career, she served as secretary to the Ministry of Labour in the first Labour government and became the first woman cabinet member when she was appointed Minister of Labour in 1929. Upon retirement in 1939 she devoted much of her time to social-service groups. Her autobiography, entitled A Life's Work (1949), concerned mainly with the "radical" causes for which she worked.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, clippings, speeches, publications, government documents, and other printed material concerning her involvement in the Labour Party and its election campaigns, 1919-1947; unemployment insurance, strikes, and juvenile employment, 1912-1931; political trip to Russia in 1920; political and labor concerns in Australia, 1929-1941; British immigration to Canada, 1924-1938; postwar affairs in Germany, 1946-1947; trips to America, 1910-1949; and various women's groups including the International Congress of Working Women, Women's Group on Public Welfare, National Institute of Houseworkers, the Shaw Training School, and the Women's Peace Crusade, 1921-1940. Correspondents include Helen Lockwood, Edith and Grace Abbott, Clement Atlee, Angelica Balabanoff, Martha Anderson, Mary Anderson, William H. Beveridge, Ernst Bevan, Edward Carpenter, Madame Joliet-Curie, Mary Dingman, David Lilienthal, J. Ramsey MacDonald, Violet Markham, Frieda S. Miller, Mrs. Vijaylaxmi Pandit, Frances Perkins, Eleanor Roosevelt, Rose Schneiderman, and Lillian Wald. Personal and travel diaries, 1898, 1908, 1910-1951. Correspondence with John Hilton and Percy Wallis concerning wage and price controls, 1932. Bondfield's articles, broadcasts, speeches, and related correspondence, 1902-1948, and clippings about her, 1898-1949.
Manuscripts of her books, MY LEISURE, 1947, and A LIFE'S WORK, 1948. Family correspondence, 1896-1948, three letters to her father William Bondfield from Samuel Blasdale in America, 1854-1861, and manuscript on local history by J.S. Bondfield, 1880. Miscellaneous memorabilia, photographs, bibliographies, and notes on the collections.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Lockwood, Helen Drusilla, approximately 1891-1971; Abbott, Edith, 1876-1957; Abbott, Grace, 1878-1939; Atlee, C. R. (Clement Richard), 1883-1967; Balabanoff, Angelica, 1878-1965; Anderson, Martha; Anderson, Mary, 1872-1964; Beveridge, William Henry Beveridge, Baron, 1879-1963; Bevan, Ernst; Carpenter, Edward, 1844-1929; Joliet-Curie, Irène, 1897-1956; Dingman, Mary Agnes, 1875-1961; Lilienthal, David, 1899-1981; MacDonald, James Ramsey, 1866-1937; Markham, Violet R. (Violet Rosa); Miller, Frieda Segelke, 1889-1973; Perkins, Frances, 1882-1965; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962; Schneiderman, Rose, 1882-; Wald, Lillian D., 1867-1940; Hilton, John, 1880-1943; Wallis, Percy; Bondfield, William; Blasdale, Samuel; Pandir, Vijaya Lakshmir, 1900-; Bondfield family; Bondfield, J.S.
Organizations:
Trades Union Congress; National Federation of Women Workers; Women's Trade Union League; International Labour Organisation; Labour Party (Great Britain); International Congress of Working Women; Women's Group on Public Welfare (England); National Institute of Houseworkers; Shaw Training School; Women's Peace Crusade
Subjects:
Trade-unions--Great Britain--Societies, etc.; Women--Great Britain--Societies and clubs; Women--Great Britain--Diaries; Women--Great Britain--Social conditions; Women in politics--Great Britain; Women and peace; Women--Great Britain--Employment; Children--Employment; Elections--Great Britain; Labor and laboring classes--Great Britain; Insurance, Unemployment--Great Britain; Strikes and lockouts--Great Britain; Labor and laboring classes--Australia; World War, 1939-1945--Germany; Wage-price policy--Great Britain; Women's rights--Great Britain; Civil rights--Great Britain; Women social reformers; Feminists
Places:
Great Britain--Social conditions--20th century; Great Britain--Economic conditions--20th century; Canada--Emigration and immigration; Great Britain--Emigration and immigration; Soviet Union--Description and travel; Soviet Union--Politics and government--1917-1936; Australia--Politics and government--1901-1945; Germany--Economic conditions--1945-; Germany--Social conditions--1945-; United States--Description and travel
Document Types:
Photographs; Diaries
VCL Categories
Politics; War and War Crimes; Women's History
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, November 2006.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Estate of Helen Lockwood, VC 1912.
Series List
- Series I. Biographical Material and Ephemera, (Boxes 1 and 12)
- Series II. Family Material, (Boxes 1-2)
- Series III. Labour Party and Election Campaigns, (Boxes 3-5)
- Series IV. Russia, 1920; (Box 5A)
- Series V. Trips to America and Folders on Organizations, (Boxes 6, 6A and 7)
- Series VI. Miscellaneous, (Boxes 7-11)
- Series VII. Books and other Published Material
Container List
- Series I. Biographical Material and Ephemera
  - Lists relating to the collection and notes about Helen Lockwood's acquaintance with Margaret Bondfield and her interest in editing the papers (Folder 1.1)
  - Biographical information, including The Intractable Million: Margaret Bondfield and Unemployment Insurance, by Barbara Winkler, 1974 (Folder 1.2)
  - Diaries, 1898, 1908, 1910-1912 (Folder 12.1)
  - Diaries, 1913-1915 (Folder 12.2)
  - Diaries, 1916-1918 (Folder 12.3)
  - Diaries, 1919-1920 (Folder 12.4)
  - Diaries, 1921-1923 (Folder 12.5)
  - Diaries, 1924-1925 (Folder 12.6)
  - Diaries, 1926-1927 (Folder 12.7)
  - Diaries, 1928-1930 (Folder 12.8)
  - Diaries, 1932-1934 (Folder 12.9)
  - Diaries, 1935, 1937-1939 (Folder 12.10)
  - Diaries, 1940-1942 (Folder 12.11)
  - Diaries, 1943-1946 (Folder 12.12)
  - Diaries, 1947-1948 (Folder 12.13)
  - Diaries, 1949 (Folder 12.14)
  - Diaries, 1950-1951 (Folder 12.15)
  - Miscellaneous notebooks (Folder 12.16)
  - Bondfield passports (Folder 12.17)
  - Union membership cards (Folder 12.18)
  - Bondfield business cards (Folder 12.19)
  - Fragments of address books (Folder 12.20)
  - Travel brochures (Folder 12.21)
  - Road maps (Folder 12.22)
  - Picture postcards (Folder 12.23)
  - Clippings about Bondfield (Folder 12.24)
  - Press clippings about Bondfield, 1938 (Oversize Multi-Collection Box)
  - American newspaper clippings, 1948-1949 (Folder 12.25)
  - Galley fragment Also, a folio of US. press cuttings, 1938 (Folder 12.26)
- Series II. Family Material
  - A manuscript, "Glimpses of Local History," by J.S. Bondfield, 1880 (Folder 1.3)
  - William Bondfield [father of M.B.]. Includes 3 letters from Samuel Blasdale, a friend who came to America in 1853, 1854-1861 (Folder 1.4)
  - Rev. George Taylor [grandfather]. (Folder 1.5)
  - Annie [sister]. (Folder 1.6)
  - Katie [sister]. (Folder 1.7)
  - Frank [brother] and Rose (Folder 1.8)
  - Rev. George Henry Bondfield [brother]. (Folder 1.9)
  - Harriet Taylor [aunt]. (Folder 1.10)
  - Bondfield family correspondence, 1896-1948 (Folder 1.11)
  - Stringfellow aeroplane (Folder 1.12)
  - Programs, invitations, and public appeals. (Folder 1.13)
  - Companion of Honor Congratulations, 1948 (Folder 1.14)
  - Passports (Folder 1.15)
  - Pictures (Folder 1.16)
  - Pictures (Folder 1.17)
  - Communications from the Royal Family (Folder 1.18)
  - Programs and news items, Silver Jubilee of George V, coronation of George VI, etc (Folder 1.19)
  - Biographical information on about 20 individuals, including Jane Assams, Keir Hardie, Margaret McDonald, and H.G. Wells. (Folder 1.20)
  - Correspondence with: Edith Abbott, Grace Abbott, Martha Anderson, Clement Atlee, Angelica Balabanoff, William H. Beveridge, Ernst Bevan, Edward Carpenter, Madam Joliet-Curie, Mary Dingman, David Lilienthal, Helen Lockwood, J. Ramsey MacDonald, Violet Markham, Frieda S. Miller, Mrs.Vijaylaxmi Pandit, Frances Perkins, Eleanor Roosevelt, Rose Schneiderman, and Lillian Wald. (Box 2)
- Series III. Labour Party and election campaigns
  - Labour Party newspapers and campaign literature and M.B. campaign speeches, 1920-1947 (Folder 3.1)
  - Parliamentary candidature, Northampton, 1919-1932 (Folder 3.2)
  - Correspondence and campaign literature Wallsend, including by-election, July 1926 (Folder 3.3 -3.4)
  - Wallsend cases (Folder 3.5)
  - Letters of congratulation on appointment as Minister of Labor, 1929 (Folder 3.6)
  - Letters regarding resignation and other correspondence on politics, 1931 (Folder 3.7)
  - General election followed by an album of clippings and pictures, 1935 (Folder 3.8)
  - Chard (Somerset) (Folder 3.9)
  - Financial correspondence, reports and balance sheets, 1926-1935 (Folder 3.10)
  - Public-address equipment (Folder 3.11)
  - Miscellaneous Labour Party publications (Folder 3.12)
  - Insurance Bill, 1912 (Folder 4.1)
  - Unemployment insurance, including Special National Conference and the Blanesburgh Report, 1926-1927 (Folder 4.2-4.4)
  - General Strike, File of The British Worker, official strike news bulletin, 1926 (Folder 4.5)
  - Books for Children bill, 1928 (Folder 4.6)
  - Juvenile Employment (Folder 4.7)
  - Minister of Labour (Folder 4.8)
  - Miscellaneous white papers from government departments, 1930-1931 (Folder 4.9)
  - Rationalization, 1931 (Folder 4.10)
  - Cabinet crisis, 1931 (Folder 4.11)
  - Miscellaneous government publications (Folder 4.12)
  - Correspondence with Australia and New Zealand, 1929-1941 (Folder 5.1)
  - Canada and the British Overseas Settlement Delegation. Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings, 1924 (Folder 5.2 -5.4)
  - Canada. Resumption of British immigration and Page Croft-Dalgleish tour of British Colombia, 1938 (Folder 5.5)
  - Overseas Settlement Committee, 1931 (Folder 5.6)
  - Germany. Control Commission for Germany. British Elementary Education Branch. Includes documents, briefings, reports, correspondence, and more. Also, a trip to Switzerland, 1946-1947 (Folder 5.7 -5.8)
- Series IV. Russia 1920
  - "Russian Diary,", 7-30 May 1920; (MS) (Folder 5A.1)
  - "Russian Diary,", 7-30 May 1920; (TS) (Folder 5A.2)
  - "Russian Diary" - including Stockholm en route to Reval, 7-19 May 1920; (TS) (Folder 5A.3)
  - "Russian Diary", 31 May - 16 Jul 1920; (TS) (Folder 5A.4)
  - Reports, correspondence (Folder 5A.5- 5A.9)
  - Theatre bills (Folder 5A.10)
  - Publications (Folder 5A.11- 5A.12)
  - The Woman Worker (Folder 5A.13)
  - Speech of Smecalova (Folder 5A.14)
- Series V. Trips to America and folders on organizations
  - "American Diary" - Notes and original drafts, [1938 - 1941] (Folder 6.1)
  - "American Diary" - Original manuscript, Apr 1938 - Jan 1939 (Folder 6.2)
  - My Leisure - ms - chapters 1-6 [includes "American Diary" ], 1947 (Folder 6.3)
  - My Leisure - ms - chapters 7-8 [includes "American Diary" ], 1947 (Folder 6.4)
  - My Leisure - copy 2 - chapters 1-5 [includes "American Diary" ], 1947 (Folder 6.5)
  - My Leisure - copy 2 - chapters 6-8 [includes "American Diary" ], 1947 (Folder 6.6)
  - Correspondence re: My Leisure, 1953, 1978 (Folder 6.7)
  - Trips to U.S., 1910, 1919 (Folder 6.8)
  - Trips to U.S. - snapshots, postcards, 1910, 1919 (Folder 6.9)
  - International Labor Conference, Washington, DC, 1919 (Folder 6.10)
  - Washington Maternity Convention, 1921 (Folder 6.11)
  - Trip to U.S., 1926 - 1927 (Folder 6.12)
  - U.S. notes, 1933 (Folder 6.13)
  - U.S. press clippings, 1933 (Folder 6.14)
  - Collected U.S. publications, 1933 (Folder 6.15)
  - Collected U.S. government publications, 1933 (Folder 6.16)
  - Notes and correspondence, 1938 (Folder 6.17)
  - Collected U.S. press clippings, 1934 - 1943 (Folder 6.18)
  - "American Diary,", 17 June1938 (Folder 6A.1)
  - "American Diary,", 27 June 1938 (Folder 6A.2)
  - "American Diary,", 26 June - 7 July [1938] (Folder 6A.3)
  - "American Diary,", 12 July - 6 Aug [1938] (Folder 6A.4)
  - "American Diary,", 7-10 Aug [1938] (Folder 6A.5)
  - "American Diary,", 1-11 Sept [1938] (Folder 6A.6)
  - "American Diary,", 1-18 Sept [1938] (Folder 6A.7)
  - "American Diary,", 1-22 Sept [1938] (Folder 6A.8)
  - "American Diary,", 23 Sept - 30 Oct [1938] (Folder 6A.9)
  - "American Diary,", 19 Sept - 9 Nov [1938] (Folder 6A.10)
  - "American Diary,", 4 - 30 Nov [1938] (Folder 6A.11)
  - "American Diary" - Berea College, Kentucky (Folder 6A.12)
  - "American Diary" - Chinsegut Hill Sanctuary, 24 May 1938 (Folder 6A.13)
  - "American Diary" - Civilian Conservation Corps camps (Folder 6A.14)
  - "American Diary" - Cincinnati, The City Charter Committee (Folder 6A.15)
  - "American Diary" - Education and Housing, 15 Aug 1938 (Folder 6A.16)
  - "American Diary" - Lessons I Have Learned in America (Folder 6A.17)
  - "American Diary" - The Ministry of Laborand the Trade Unions, 20 Aug 1938 (Folder 6A.18)
  - "American Diary" - President Cardenas and Petroleum (Folder 6A.19)
  - "American Diary" - Ramon Beteta, 29 July 1938 (Folder 6A.20)
  - "American Diary" - Interview with Trotsky, Aug 1938 (Folder 6A.21)
  - "American Diary" - The TVA (Folder 6A.22)
  - "American Diary" - Unemployment Service and Social Security, 31 May 1938 (Folder 6A.23)
  - Programs, speeches, and publications relating to American trips, 1938 and 1941-43, and undated American papers. Includes report on a trip to Mexico, 1938, 1938/1941-1943 (Folder 7.1)
  - American trips, and undated American papers. Includes report on a trip to Mexico. (Folder 7.2)
  - American correspondence, 1942-1943 (Folder 7.3)
  - Grand Coulee Dam, 1938 (Folder 7.3A)
  - Publications relating to social security, 1939 (Folder 7.3B)
  - American magazines and documents, 1940 (Folder 7.4)
  - American magazines, 1943-1945 (Folder 7.5)
  - Correspondence relating to American trip, 1948-1949 (Folder 7.6)
- Series VI. Miscellaneous
  - International Labour Conference and International Congress of Working Women, 1921 (Folder 7.7)
  - Correspondence with John Hilton and Percy Wallis relating to wage and price levels, 1932 (Folder 7.8)
  - Miscellaneous publications relating to labor unions and women workers. (Folder 7.9)
  - Women's Group on Public Welfare. Includes correspondence, programs, and publications. (Folder 7.10)
  - Central Committee on Women's Training and Employment (Folder 7.11)
  - National Institute of Houseworkers (Folder 7.12)
  - Residential College for Working Women (Folder 7.13)
  - The Shaw Training School, 1939-1940 (Folder 7.14)
  - The Mary MacArthur Holiday Home (Folder 7.15)
  - Church of England and Church of England Advisory Council of Empire Settlement (Folder 7.16)
  - Women's International League, Women's Peace Crusade, etc. (Folder 7.17)
  - Papers relating to action postponed or canceled because of declaration of war, and proposals made during the war, Sept. 1939 (Folder 7.18)
  - War memorials (Folder 7.19)
  - Temperance (Folder 7.20)
  - Over-Thirty Association (Folder 7.21)
  - 2 manuscript copies of autobiography, A Life's Work (London: Hutchinson, 1948); additional copies of some chapters and source materials (Folder 8.1-8.3)
  - Press cuttings about A Life's Work (Folder 8.4)
  - Correspondence relating to A Life's Work (Folder 8.5)
  - Illustrations for A Life's Work (Folder 8.6)
  - Manuscripts of poetry and stories by M.B. (Folder 8.7)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Folder 8.8)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Folder 8.9)
  - Essays by George Baker (mostly relating to international situation and World War II), late 1930's (Folder 8.10)
  - Miscellaneous Labour Party pamphlets and Fabian tracts. (Folder 8.11)
  - Miscellaneous publications and pamphlets relating to religion (Folder 8.12)
  - Miscellaneous brochures, articles, and papers (Folder 8.13)
  - Lists of articles published by M.B., 1909-1945 (Folder 9.1)
  - Articles, 1909-1922 (Folder 9.2)
  - Articles and correspondence, 1923-1945 (Folder 9.3-9.9)
  - Broadcasts and correspondence, 1928-1948 (Folder 9.10-9.13)
  - Speeches, 1916-1948 (Folder 9.14)
  - Press cuttings, 1898-1948 (Boxes 10-11)
- Series VII. Books and other Published Material
  - Attlee, Clement R. The Labour Party Perspective. London: V. Gollancz, 1937.
  - British Broadcasting Corporation. BBC Handbook 1940. London, British Broadcasting Corporation, n.d.
  - Church of England. The Book of Common Prayer... Together with the Psalter... London: Eyre and Spottiswoode.
  - Henry, Alice. Memoirs of Alice Henry. Ed. with postscript by Nettie Palmer. Melbourne, 1944. 101p. Mimeographed, in binder
  - Hilton, John. Industrial Relations. Cambridge: University Press, 1931. Pamphlet.
  - Huxley, Julian. What Dare I Think? London: Chatto and Windus, 1931.
  - K-H News-Letter Service. Vol. two, Letters 27-52 (Dec.30, 1936-June 16,1937). Bound.
  - Mansbridge, Albert. Margaret McMillan, Prophet and Pioneer London and Toronto: M. Dent and Sons [1932].
  - Manual of Procedure in the Public Business of the House of Commons. 5th ed. London: His Majesty's Stationary Office, 1924.
  - National Adult School Union, London. Towards a Whole Society; a Scheme of Study for the Year 1946. London, National Adult School Union [1945]
  - The New Poetry; an Anthology. Ed. by Harriet Monroe and Alice Corbin Henderson. New York: MacMillan, 1919.
  - Plummer, Alfred. Labour's Path to Power. Foreword by Margaret Bondfield. London: Richards Press [1929?]
  - Reed, John. Ten Days That Shook the World. New York: Boni and Liveright, 1919.
  - Tangore, Rabindranath. Sadhana. London: MacMillan, 1917
  - Wald, Lillian D. Windows on Henry Street. Boston: Little Brown, 1934. Autograph card pasted on flyleaf.
  - Whitman, Walt. Poems of Walt Whitman (from 'Leaves of Grass'), with introduction by Ernest Rhys. London: Walter Scott, n.d. (The Canterbury poets).
  - Williams, Francis. Fifty Years March. London: Odhams Press, n.d.